Björn Persson
Poste restante
631 01 Eskilstuna
Sweden

bjorn(at)kiltedviking.net.nospam (exchange "(at)" with "@" and remove ".nospam")1

Björn Persson - Curriculum Vitae

Who is Björn?

I was born in Båstad in the south of Sweden in 1970 by a Swedish father and a Scottish mother. Most of my summers were spent in Scotland visiting my grandmother and aunt. This, and my mother speaking English to me, means I am bilingual and am fluent in both Swedish and English. Five years has also been spent studying German - a language I understand and might be able to speak again with some practice.

I now live in Eskilstuna, a town "just" west of Stockholm, home of Volvo Construction Equipment and ASSA/Abloy. In 1996 I was employed by the University and I bought a house here in 1999, which I sold in 2006.

My interest for computers started when my childhood friend lured me to start, what was to become, one of Sweden's largest BBS:es² (multiple phone lines, computers, CD-ROM switchers, etc.). Shortly after that I bought my own computer, a computer I've extended, and replaced, quite a few times. When I had enough hardware I built my own network at home to help me learn more about computers and networking.

I like computers (and other electronic things) and solving computer-related problems as it requires me to learn new things all the time.

Education

Compulsory school in Sweden is nine years preparing you for "optional" (upper) secondary school (three to five years), to be followed by studies at University.

1986-89	Upper secondary school with specialisation in structural engineering (sv. <i>byggteknik</i>), Laholm/Halmstad
1992-95	Computer Science, Computer Engineering, Mathematics, and Information Systems at Växjö University
1995-96	Information Systems, and Computer Science at Mälardalen University
2000/02	Information Systems at Örebro University

2007-07-22

¹ My e-mail address has been "obscured" to avoid getting SPAM as CV is published on the Internet.

² BBS: Bulletin Board System, "the way" of communicating via computers before the Internet.

Björn Persson Curriculum Vitae

My studies at secondary school have been related to engineering but also included German and other non-engineering subjects. The last year I spent studying structural engineering (house building). After working a couple of years (see below) I went on to University studying computer science, computer engineering, mathematics, and information systems. After finishing my bachelor thesis (B.A.) in information systems, and started working, I kept on studying to expand my knowledge, mainly in information systems. (My employers have been nice enough to spend money on courses in handling customers and computer technologies – like Novell NetWare).

During my studies I have come in contact with programming languages like Ada, Pascal, Smalltalk, Eiffel, Prolog, C/C++, Visual Basic (5/6), Java, and assembler (Motorola 68000). Databases (or rather DBMS:s) I have used are Paradox, Access (Jet), Oracle and MySQL. The programming has been done on different platforms (PC, Mac, UNIX computers) using different operating systems (DOS, Windows, OS/2, MacOS, Linux, and UNIX).

Work experience

1989-91	Administrator for Fältbiologerna (a youth organisation for field biology), Halmstad
1990-93	Ground keeper, receptionist, and more at KronoCamping Båstad/Torekov (seasonal)
1991-92	Military service at weather service, Ängelholm
1994	Sales, distribution, and support of CD-ROMs and multimedia products, Buller Data AB, Båstad
1995	Application developer, Medicinsk Teknik, Eskilstuna
1996-2006	System administrator, lecturer, and student career counsellor at School of Business, Mälardalen University, Eskilstuna/Västerås

As administrator for the Field biologists I ran the office where I answered the phone, arranged courses (booking halls and the like), spoke at schools about the organisation, and more. This was partly voluntary work (badly paid) and only during school year. The rest of the year I worked for the camping site KronoCamping Båstad/Torekov as a "handy man", i.e. doing what needed to be done.

Military service is (was?) compulsory and I spent 341 days looking at the weather, reporting it to the air traffic controllers and Swedish weather service (SMHI). During my service I managed to keep on working hours at the camp site.

In a break in University studies I worked for a small company, Buller Data AB, selling CD-ROM (which were news in 1994) and multimedia products. Being a small company (at most 4 employees) one took part in most of the running of the business. This included distribution (packaging) and customer support for sold products. (Buller Data AB moved on and started Sverige.net and became an Internet service provider for southern Sweden.)

2007-07-22

Björn Persson Curriculum Vitae

During my lecturing at university I have taught in programming languages like Visual Basic (6), Visual C++, Smalltalk, Java, and C# using DMBS like Access (Jet), Oracle, SQL Server, and MySQL. I have also taught on subjects like database theory and design, and object oriented programming (i.e. the theory of OOP and how to implement it in Java). On a course about component-based development I taught both COM/COM+/.NET and J2EE using both desktop (local) and web-based clients. Most of the education has been done in a Microsoft environment (DOS/Windows).

One of my strengths (and according to students who have told me) is to be able to explain computer-related problems/technologies to less computer literary people. I can "lower" myself to their level of knowledge and try to use terms in their area of knowledge as metaphors.

As a system administrator I have installed and maintained computer rooms with operating systems varying between DOS/Windows 3.x to XP using servers running Novell NetWare (3.12 to 6) and Windows NT/2000/2003. Server software I have installed and maintained are Oracle, SQL Server, web servers (IIS and Apache), and application servers (among others Resin for J2EE). As a system administrator my job was also to maintain and develop the department's web site using HTML, CSS, SSI, PHP, and some older systems in ASP. Data was stored in MySQL and Oracle servers.

Interests

I find problem solving the most interesting. It's a way of learning more and it's gratifying to solve a problem. Helping others is also rewarding for me and I like sharing my knowledge with others. While helping others I will do what needs to be done, regardless if it is part of my work description or not, if there is no one else to do the job better.

The last couple of years I have focused on J2EE and PHP/MySQL while becoming, among other things, fascinated by how well Sun has created J2EE.

During my years I have tried to avoid user interfaces (GUIs) and Perl – two thing I feel other people are more competent at handling (as I believe my homepages, http://www.kiltedviking.net/, proves ©).

Private projects

I have some private computer-related projects, which I started to developing as part of a course at Örebro University (2000), and to summarize for myself and to help students on courses I taught. These projects are **only in Swedish** (as that is the preferred language of students I taught).

- My study web web-based knowledgebase for HTML, CSS, JavaScript, ASP, PHP, and Java. (http://www.kiltedviking.net/se/www/)
- My summaries PDF files with summaries about COM/COM+/.NET, J2EE, web-based development, and installing development and server software (like Apache, MySQL, PHP, Resin, and Oracle).

(http://www.kiltedviking.net/se/sammanfattningar/)

A more current version of this CV might be found at http://www.kiltedviking.net/cv/.

2007-07-22